<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title>Wunderdog K-9 Care &amp; Training</title>
	<link href="http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdog"/>
	<updated>2016-02-09T00:33:12.198Z</updated>
	<id>http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdog</id>
	<author>
		<name>Lynn Wunderli</name>
		<email>wunderdogwi@yahoo.com</email>
	</author>
	<entry>
		<title>We&#39;re a &quot;Best of Madison&quot; Dog Training Winner!</title>
		<link href="http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdogposts/best-of-madison-2016.html"/>
		<updated>2016-02-18T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
		<id>http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdog</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re very proud to announce that we have taken the honor of the Silver in the
2016 Best of Madison Dog Training category!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry><entry>
		<title>Winter Wolf Ecology Workshop 2014</title>
		<link href="http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdogposts/winter-wolf-ecology-workshop-2014.html"/>
		<updated>2014-02-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
		<id>http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdog</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;February in northern Wisconsin is not most couple&#39;s idea of a &quot;getaway.&quot; But, if you are Lynn and Peter (Wunderli), you might beg to differ!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Peter and I share a love for outdoor winter sports, and have a great respect and enthusiasm about protection of our natural resources. Couple these reasons with my interest in innate dog behavior (and Peter&#39;s support of this), made signing up for TWIN&#39;s (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.timberwolfinformation.org&quot;&gt;Timber Wolf Information Network&lt;/a&gt;) workshop on Wolf Ecology an easy choice!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before moving to Wisconsin, we did informal tracking of coyotes in New Hampshire. I had always yearned for more... unfortunately, the prospect of wolf tracking was never an option in New England (they have been exterminated), so when the opportunity presented itself in our new State of Wisconsin, we both jumped on it! We arose very early on Saturday morning (2/8) and drove up to Babcock, WI. We arrived and checked into the TWIN facility (basic dorm rooms with bunks) where we were greeted with friendly faces and coffee (not to mention other breakfast items!). Soon after arriving, we met Deb, a volunteer with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wolf.org&quot;&gt;International Wolf Center&lt;/a&gt; (Ely, MN). She and about 7 others from IWC came down for the weekend workshop to learn more about the wolves they so graciously house at their center in ELY. We met Rob Schultz, Executive Director for IWC, who had attended TWIN&#39;s Wolf Ecology Workshop the year before (and was so impressed he brought his crew back for this year&#39;s workshop!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amount of education you receive from this workshop is immense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You learn about plant life and its affect on/from wildlife, the natural history (evolution) of the canid (dog species), the biology of the wolf (and other canid species as well as ungulates), communication within the wolf communities, population and mortality trends of wolves (and ungulates), the core value system of humans and how our ancestral history affects the way we see wolves today, the hunting and illegal poaching of wolves-- to the current &quot;harvesting&quot; of wolves and why this is actually good and necessary in COMPLETE moderation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to learn all of these things, and more. For me as a canine trainer, I need to continue to learn about canids in every way I possibly can. Acquiring knowledge in wolf behavior will better my ability to help clients communicate with their dogs, as learning about wolf behavior can give humans great insight into their dog&#39;s behavior (article to follow).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more about wildlife preservation and education, go to these following sites:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.timberwolfinformation.org&quot;&gt;Timber Wolf Information Network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wolf.org&quot;&gt;International Wolf Center&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dnr.wi.gov&quot;&gt;Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
	</entry><entry>
		<title>In The News...</title>
		<link href="http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdogposts/in-the-news.html"/>
		<updated>2012-07-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
		<id>http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdog</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lynn presented &quot;CBADDC&quot; (Canine Behavior and Doggie Day Care) at the popular New England Pet Grooming Professionals (NEPGP) Summerfest in Warwick, RI on July 14, 2012. While attending and presenting, Lynn was taken by surprise to find out her clients, had voted her TOP DOG in NEPGP&#39;s annual contest (derived soley from client voting)! It was a great honor and testimonial to Wunderdog! Lynn wishes to THANK each and every one of her Wunderdog families for taking the time to vote and making her feel incredibly loved and valued!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry><entry>
		<title>Gilda The Great Book Update!</title>
		<link href="http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdogposts/gilda-the-great-book-update.html"/>
		<updated>2012-05-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
		<id>http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdog</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As most of our clients have already heard, Lynn and her daughter Laney (an artist/illustrator/animator/videographer) have started their first book about &quot;Gilda,&quot; the sweet little character Laney rescued from a shelter out west. Laney has begun the illustrations, and we are hoping to complete the book in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book will center around Gilda&#39;s start in her new life with &quot;Ida Mae McDougal,&quot; a elderly ranch owner in Sante Fe, NM. Special little Gilda will be named &quot;Gilda Rose McDougal&quot; for unique reasons by Ida Mae. What is even more interesting is that the book is based on the true story of Gilda&#39;s rescue (a cause near-and-dear to all of our hearts!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;STAY TUNED for sneak peeks, pictures and progress-updates!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry><entry>
		<title>Choosing The Right Breed For You and Your Family</title>
		<link href="http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdogposts/choosing-the-right-breed.html"/>
		<updated>2012-03-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
		<id>http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdog</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dogs of many sizes, shapes and personalities are available for purchase or adoption. The main thing that you, the potential owner, must recognize and understand, is that BEFORE you commit, you must have all the facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you want an athletic dog? A dog that is sedentary? A fast learner? A &quot;vocal dog?&quot; A friendly-to-all-people dog? A dog to alert you in the case of danger? What type of daily (or weekly) brushing or combing would you find reasonable? How much money are you willing to spend on routine supplies such as food or professional grooming? WHat about potential health issues common to a specific breed? Do you want a toy, small, medium, large, or giant breed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often following a movie that is based on a particular type dog, there is an increase in that breed&#39;s sales. Problem is, the people that want &quot;a dog that looks like the cute character in the movie&quot; don&#39;t understand the breed&#39;s traits or tendencies and how those may not &quot;jive&quot; with that person or their family. They just think the dog in the movie is cute, funny, or smart - and they want one just like it...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even when adopting a dog from a shelter, it is important (when information is available) to understand the characteristics of the ALL the breeds that make up a &quot;mixed breed.&quot; If you are not interested in a &quot;vocal&quot; dog, do not get a Beagle, a Norweigan Elkhound, or a Jack Russell Terrier! If you do not wish to be vacuuming daily, do not purchase a Siberian Husky, an Akita, a Golden Retriever, a PUG (not to mention the many short haired breeds such as Pointers or Labradors whose straight hairs are very stubborn about being removed from any carpet or fibrous surface)! If you cannot afford professional grooming, do not get a &quot;hair-dog&quot; that will require a professional grooming every 4 to 8 weeks (not to mention daily combing and brushing). You get the picture....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wunderdog offers a &quot;Breed Referral Service&quot; that can take a lot of the hassle out of finding the right breed of dog for you and your family. Using this service can save you time and possible heartache often associated with making the wrong choices or a spontaneous purchase of a dog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, we are a liaison for &quot;PAWS New England&quot; (a non-profit dog rescue organization) and can help you select one of the many dogs in need of a good home. Call or email us today to find out how we can help you make the best decision possible about adding a four-footer to your family - whether purchasing a purebred dog, or adopting a rescue!﻿﻿﻿﻿&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about our daycamp program, go to the main menu and choose &quot;Camp Wunderdog.&quot;﻿
What&#39;s so great about sending your dog to &quot;daycare,&quot; or in Wunderdog&#39;s case, &quot;daycamp&quot;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons to do it, here are the TOP TEN:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It gives your dog (or puppy) socialization with other canines in a safe, relaxed setting (very important to a dog&#39;s happiness).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It offers you a &quot;guilt-free&quot; day knowing that your dog is having FUN, and being fulfilled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your daily training (manners, etc.) are reinforced in a positive way (all Wunderdogs have to sit at entrances and exits; they are taught to &quot;wait,&quot; have group obedience, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your dog will receive structure - something very important to a dog&#39;s piece-of-mind; we play HARD, but we positively reinforce &quot;order&quot; - for all our dog&#39;s safety and mental health.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have a puppy, and you need to work, your pup will be trained during your working hours! It costs about the same as having someone come into your home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your dog hasn&#39;t been properly socialized with people and/or other dogs, daycamp is one way to start acclimating him/her - this spills over to every day life!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your dog will receive true cardio exercise; if you are looking to get your dog &quot;fit,&quot; look no further!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your dog will receive crate-time (short intervals) which reinforces the crate as a happy, safe-haven. Crating is a dog&#39;s &quot;den,&quot; and should be a comfortable place for your dog to go to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daycamp is a great way for you to learn about your dog&#39;s innate behavior. It is good training for both owner and dog in the art of communication - your Wundercare giver will always lend an ear to you, and provide a voice for your dog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your dog will learn to trust other humans (outside of your &quot;pack&quot;) - this is important for many reasons - but mainly for transitioning into different and necessary scenarios (examples: vet care, grooming, boarding, traveling, etc.). He/she will be exposed to many sounds and sights DIFFERENT from your home - again, this is great exposure for your dog!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
	</entry><entry>
		<title>Backyard Breeders.... Who are They?</title>
		<link href="http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdogposts/backyard-breeders.html"/>
		<updated>2012-02-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
		<id>http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdog</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-this-title-mean-&quot;&gt;What does this title mean?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;﻿These are the people, who purchase a &quot;purebred&quot; dog with (most likely) AKC or &quot;America&#39;s Pet Registry, Inc.&quot; papers who think that their animal is a good candidate for breeding. The reasoning usually goes like this: &quot;I want my children to experience a mother giving birth and caring for her offspring.&quot; Or, &quot;We think our dog is so wonderful, she should have puppies so that other people can have a wonderful dog too.&quot; Perhaps they say, &quot;I&#39;d like my in-tact male to experience &lt;strong&gt;__&lt;/strong&gt;.&quot; Whatever the reason, it&#39;s not a GOOD ENOUGH reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Backyard Breeders do not test for potential genetic diseases, general health screenings, or the establishment of documented certification (examples: AKC conformation championship titles, agility and obedience titles, working titles, etc.). They are the folks that think they can actually MAKE MONEY off breeding their animals! Let me tell you, if you are a reputable breeder, by the time you get your dog trained, titled, health and genetically-sound certified, you are already &quot;in the hole.&quot; Now, you then, in order to breed to a very good candidate, will do specific pedigree research to find the best possible breeding (to improve your breed) mate. Any dog that is proven in the ring (whether it be conformation, working, agility, obedience, etc.) is not going to be inexpensive to breed to. And THEN, you have the pregnancy and the related health maintenance (you must supplement the bitch, exercise her regularly, etc.), the whole preparation for the whelping, the actual whelping (you must be ready for complications!), and the chores of taking care of a litter properly (figure on at least 8 weeks of 3 hrs of chores daily).  YOU DO NOT MAKE MONEY BREEDING ANIMALS. ANYONE WHO TELLS YOU THEY DO, IS NOT BEING HONEST. The only reason to breed our purebreds is to maintain and improve the quality of our dogs. And, even in today&#39;s economy and with all the unwanted animals at shelters, I have to question the validity of this for even the small, reputable breeder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These backyard breeders breed different purebreds together to create a mix that they feel will be &quot;cute,&quot; or &quot;easy to sell.&quot; OUR PUREBRED DOGS HAVE BEEN AROUND FOR HUNDREDS OF YEARS. Their bloodlines have been improved and maintained for the purpose of QUALITY and HEALTH. You cannot possibly know enough about your two separate (or more) breeds and their past genetic struggles or lines of improvement (or detriment) to know what you are doing in mixing the two!!! It is a pathetic attempt at making money and feeling personally &quot;creative.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really feel that people forget that purebreds, no matter what breed they are, have been created for a purpose. They were created to perform jobs. If you truly take this into consideration, you would only leave the breeding to the experts. They make it their LIFE to breed the best and most suitable dogs--for the reasons they were created in the first place. They do countless acts of volunteer work for their breed&#39;s organizations, they spend countless hours training and maintaining their dogs... they spend large amounts of money showing and competing. When their dogs are bred, they do extensive interviews with potential purchasing candidates, only to &quot;approve&quot; the appropriate homes. They STRONGLY encourage buyers to involve their animals in activities most geared towards their innate drives and talents. They offer guidance throughout the life of the animal they are selling, and try to involve the buyer in joining pertinent organizations for their breed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sad-story&quot;&gt;Sad Story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A client of mine lives next door to a family who, in the beginning of their &quot;friendship,&quot; owned three dogs. Two older ones (both NOT fixed), and then a new German Shepherd puppy, purchased from a &quot;reputable breeder.&quot; When I met them socially, this pup was about 6 months old. He was clearly unfocused, ill-behaved (no structure, no training), and still in-tact. They complained to me, as a trainer, about his running away, not complying to their (inconsistent) commands, etc...I asked them when they were going to neuter him. Their reply was that they thought they might &quot;breed him.&quot; That, &quot;he is out of wonderful German bloodlines,&quot; and that they &quot;wanted him to experience one breeding before fixing him.&quot;  I gave them my &quot;speech&quot; (above) and information, and they, of course, remained undeterred. These same people kept their new, &quot;prized&quot; big boy in a 6X6 enclosure, along with a (debilitated) in-tact 12 yr old female Collie (who was in heat when I met them) and an older (smaller) breed for 10 hours at a day. About 6 months ago, they purchased another purebred German Shepherd from a &quot;reputable breeder.&quot; She too has &quot;wonderful bloodlines&quot; (like they would know ANYTHING about bloodlines) and they want to breed the two shepherds to &quot;make some money.&quot; They also believe that they shouldn&#39;t &quot;let these wonderful bloodlines go to waste.&quot; Meanwhile, these same people do not work, train, compete with, exercise, or properly confine these animals. All the dogs are running free around the neighborhood, no collars or I.D. tags on them, defecating and urinating on the adjoining properties, uncontrolled and unbalanced. Not to mention the fact that they could BREED with any other free in-tact animal! AND THESE PEOPLE ARE SOON TO HAVE A LITTER. Scary, huh? It makes me ill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-little-statistical-information-for-you&quot;&gt;A little statistical information for you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presently, there are approximately 74.8 million dogs in the United States. In 1997, the last year for the National Council on Pet Population Study and Policy to prepare a report, of the 3500 shelters actually reported as existing in the U.S., only 1000 reported their euthanasia records. This survey calculated that, of the 4.3 million animals documented, 2.7 million animals were euthanized. 56% (of those 2.7 million) were dogs. Currently it is estimated that there approximately 9.6 million animals are euthanized annually in the United States. These are alarming numbers, don&#39;t you agree? Picture the dogs that are left there--confused and alone. I have two clients in particular that were ONE WEEK from being put to sleep. They are the BEST dogs you would ever know! It breaks my heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason I am so (obviously) passionate about this issue is that I deal with the aftermath of it all...needless to say, I was HAPPY to see that The Obamas chose a purebred instead of a &quot;designer dog&quot;; and further - they adopted him.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry><entry>
		<title>To Crate, Or Not To Crate... That Is The Question!</title>
		<link href="http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdogposts/to-crate-or-not-to-crate.html"/>
		<updated>2012-01-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
		<id>http://blog.crushingpennies.com/wunderdog</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nothing brings more to the table when I first meet with a new client than crate training. Most humans view crating as a &quot;prison,&quot; or consider it cruel to confine a puppy or dog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crate training is a necessity. It a way to teach your dog to have self-restraint (holding his &quot;potty&quot;), it offers structure by creating a routine, it gives the dog a place that he can feel comfortable (consider like a bedroom), and offers you and the dog a &quot;retreat&quot; should things get chaotic in the home. A crate also encourages a pup or dog&#39;s personal cleanliness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the wild, canines have a natural &quot;order&quot; to their pack; a hierarchy system that works for them. They are content because they live in a very structured environment. They are productive (hunting, etc.) because they have &quot;order.&quot; Their &quot;crate&quot; is their cave--it represents safety and solitude. A crate, used properly in the home, offers a dog more structure, more safety, and yes--you guessed it--more solitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, as humans, do not understand their &quot;system&quot; (unless we choose to learn about it). Because there is a communication-gap between our dogs and ourselves (think of it as being in a home where you do not understand the language being spoken and you have to rely on hand and facial/mouth gestures), we have a responsibility to our pets to try and communicate better with them, and provide them an atmosphere that is conducive to what makes the most sense to them and most comfortable. I am not talking about fluffy beds and meat scraps--I am talking about giving them clear and concise &quot;household rules,&quot; and being fair and equitable in doing so. A crate is just a small help in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By crate training your dog, you are giving him/her the best gift you possibly can as a human! It will ease them into transitional periods such as vacationing, boarding, grooming, vet stays, etc. As humans, we need to understand that there will come a time when we will need to be away from our dog(s). Do you want the responsibility of creating a neurotic dog who cannot be away from you and will make him/herself physically sick because he/she cannot &quot;settle&quot; without you? Think about that... before you &quot;humanize&quot; your dog to the point of making him/her miserable without you, consider this sensible tool. Do your pup a favor and learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, a crate is not something to be &quot;abused,&quot; and I do not advocate crating for extended periods of time. Use it for training, safety, and practical purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
